A Guide to the Henry H. Bauer Papers, 1950-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Henry H. Bauer Papers, 1950-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1999-005
24.2 cu. ft. 18 boxes
The Henry H. Bauer Papers contains correspondence, grant reports, newspaper clippings, memoirs, class notes, chemistry files, evaluations, appointment books, lectures, talks, and conference materials - particularly those pertaining to the Society for Scientific Exploration (SSE). Much of the material relates to Bauer's work as academic professor and administrator, as well as his interest in the study of anomalies, especially the Loch Ness Monster.
Bauer, Henry H.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry H. Bauer Papers were donated to Special Collections between 1992 and 1999. Additional materials were donated in 2010.
Biographical Note
Born in Austria in 1931, Dr. Henry H. Bauer (Ph.D. 1956, University of Sydney, Australia) is Emeritus Professor of Chemistry and Science Studies, and Emeritus Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences (1978-1999) at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. He frequently wrote and spoke about scientific unorthodoxies (e.g., Loch Ness monster, Velikovsky), ethics in science, as well as the politics of higher education. Dr. Bauer is one of the founding members of the Society for Scientific Exploration (SSE), and served as Editor-in-Chief for the Journal of Scientific Exploration from 2000-2007. He has published several books, including The Enigma of the Loch Ness Monster: making Sense of a Mystery (1986), Beyond Velikowsky: The History of a Public Controversy (1984), and To Rise Above Principle: The Memoirs of an Unreconstructed Dean (1988), which was published under the pen-name "Josef Martin."
Scope and Content
The Henry H. Bauer Papers contains correspondence, grant reports, newspaper clippings, memoirs, class notes, chemistry files, evaluations, appointment books, lectures, talks, and conference materials - particularly those pertaining to the Society for Scientific Exploration (SSE). Conference abstracts, programs, and participant lists include notations and comments added by Bauer. Many of Bauer's talks are also accompanied by related transperancies. Much of the material relates to Bauer's work as academic professor and administrator, as well as his interest in the study of anomalies, especially the Loch Ness Monster.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series by material type: Series I: Talk, Conferences, and Publications; Series II: Teaching and Students; Series III: Academic/Administration; Series IV: Subject/Administrative Files; and Series V: Research. Within each series, files are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books have been removed from the collection and catalogued for the rare book collection:
Breyer, B. Publications, 1935-1954.
Breyer, B. Studies in Polarography and Tensammetry.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Talks, Conferences, and Publications
  - 4S - Washington, 1979 (Box-folder 17-56)
  - 4S, Blacksburg, 1983 (Box-folder 17-48)
  - A New Theory of the Earth. (Box 5)
  - About Belief - Unitarian Church, 1977 (Box-folder 17-60)
  - ACAD, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 17-12)
  - AIDS in Historical Context, 2000 (Box-folder 15-4)
  - American Electrochemists, 1976 (Box-folder 17-61)
  - Anti-SCI, Florida, 1997 (Box-folder 16-47)
  - AOACI, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 16-48)
  - APSE, 1996 (Box-folder 16-54)
  - Are Chemists Scientists?, 1989 (Box-folder 17-29)
  - Arguments about Pseudo-Science, 1986 (Box-folder 17-41)
  - At Issue, Against Reparations, n.d. (Box-folder 18-26)
  - At Issue, PBS TV - Criticizing VT Sport Infatuation, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 18-25)
  - Australia, 1993 (Box-folder 17-6)
  - Bakken Museum Talk - LNM, 1988 (Box-folder 17-33)
  - Big Science - NSF Workshop, 2000 (Box-folder 18-29)
  - Biology, 1987 (June), 1987 (Box-folder 17-36)
  - CCAS Phoenix, 1984 (Box-folder 16-9)
  - C.F. - Australia, 1993 (Box-folder 17-10)
  - Chauvinist, 1975 (Box-folder 17-63)
  - Chemistry papers and personal memos. (Box 3)
  - Controversies on the Fringes of Science, East Tenn., 1979 (Box-folder 17-59)
  - Cornell, 1996 (Box-folder 16-49)
  - Cornell, May 2000, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 16-58)
  - Council of Colleges of Arts and Sciences, Savannah, 1982 (Box-folder 16-10)
  - CS3 Workshop - Demarcation of Science & Psuedoscience, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 17-55)
  - 1st CSICOP Meeting, Buffalo, 1983 (Box-folder 17-49)
  - Double Layer Conference, 1970 (Box-folder 15-11)
  - Electrodics Reviews, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 16-17)
  - Ethics ACS Students, 1990 (Box-folder 17-24)
  - Ethics - Australia, 1993 (Box-folder 17-7)
  - Expt & Sci Change, 1990 (Box-folder 17-22)
  - Forestry, 2001 (Box-folder 18-24)
  - Forestry, 2002 (Box-folder 16-42)
  - HIV, n.d. (Box-folder 15-2)
  - HIV Ahd, n.d. (Box-folder 15-3)
  - HIV Tests Sent to CDC & Army Research Office, n.d. (Box-folder 15-1)
  - HIV/AIDS Blunder, 2006 (Box-folder 16-36)
  - IBM Santa Cruz, 1986 (Box-folder 17-37)
  - ICUS, 1986 (Box-folder 17-43)
  - ICUS, 1995 (Box-folder 16-56)
  - Indirect Costs and Greed, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 17-13)
  - ISC Meeting, Edinburgh - LNM, 1987 (Box-folder 17-34)
  - Journal, 1994-2007 (Box-folder 15-5)
  - Lawroast, 1985 (Box-folder 16-8)
  - Learning from the Velikowsky Affair, 1986 (Box-folder 17-42)
  - London XI, 1994 (Box-folder 17-1)
  - LN - ACS, 1974 (Box-folder 17-64)
  - LN, 1999 (Box-folder 16-45)
  - Michigan, 1966-1984 (Box-folder 16-2)
  - MUFON, 2008 (Box-folder 16-31)
  - Myth of S.M., 1993 (Box-folder 17-9)
  - NAS - San Francisco, 1993 (Box-folder 17-11)
  - NAS, 1994 (Box-folder 17-2)
  - NAS, 1996 (Box-folder 16-51)
  - Newspaper articles. (Box 10)
  - "Origin of Life" Prize, 2000 (Box-folder 16-24)
  - P.C. Education - Australia, 1993 (Box-folder 17-8)
  - PC Forum, 1991 (Box-folder 17-18)
  - Pop Culture - LNM, Louisville, 1982 (Box-folder 17-54)
  - Portland, 1994 (Box-folder 17-3)
  - Pseudo-Science, 1986 (Box-folder 17-39)
  - Publications, 1950-1964 (Box-folder 16-3)
  - RA, 2009 (Box-folder 16-29)
  - Reactions to speeches. (Box 10)
  - Resistance- LNM, Japan, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 17-62)
  - Revealing Josef Martin, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 17-23)
  - Reviews (ACP), 1964-1966 (Box-folder 16-18)
  - Roast, 1986 (Box-folder 16-6)
  - Science Files. (Box 13)
  - Science & Pseduoscience, 1983 (Box-folder 17-51)
  - Science & Spirituality of Healing, 2000 (Box-folder 18-27)
  - Scientists' View, 1992 (Box-folder 17-15)
  - Society for Interdisciplinary Studies (SIS) Review. (Box 4)
  - Society for Interdisciplinary Studies Workshops. (Box 4)
  - Society for Scientific Exploration, (2 folders), 1987-2007 (Box-folder 15-8 to 15-9)
  - SSE Inaugural Meeting, 1982 (Box-folder 17-53)
  - SSE, Charlottesville, 1983 (Box-folder 17-50)
  - SSE, Princeton, 1984 (Box-folder 17-47)
  - SSE, 1986 (Box-folder 17-38)
  - SSE - LNM, 1987 (Box-folder 17-35)
  - SSE - Cornell, 1988 (Box-folder 17-32)
  - SSE, 1989 (Box-folder 17-30)
  - SSE, 1990 (Box-folder 17-21)
  - SSE, 1991 (Box-folder 17-17)
  - SSE, 1992 (Box-folder 17-14)
  - SSE - Austin, 1994 (Box-folder 17-4)
  - SSE, 1995 (Box-folder 16-57)
  - SSE, Charlottesville, 1996 (Box-folder 16-52)
  - SSE, 1997 (Box-folder 16-60)
  - SSE, 1998 (Box-folder 16-59)
  - SSE, 1999 (Box-folder 16-46)
  - SSE, 2000 (Box-folder 18-28)
  - SSE, 2001 (Box-folder 18-30)
  - SSE, 2002 (Box-folder 16-41)
  - SSE, 2003 (Box-folder 16-40)
  - SSE, Paris, 2003 (Box-folder 16-39)
  - SSE, 2004 (Box-folder 16-38)
  - SSE, 2005 (Box-folder 16-37)
  - SSE, 2006 (Box-folder 16-35)
  - SSE, 2007 (Box-folder 16-34)
  - SSE, 2008 (Box-folder 16-32)
  - SSE, 2009 (Box-folder 16-30)
  - SSE Copy Edit, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 15-6)
  - S.S.P., vi 82 1982-1983 (Box-folder 17-52)
  - STS, 1994 (Box-folder 17-5)
  - Students, Advisees, PC, 1999 (Box-folder 16-44)
  - Talks - About Belief; LNM - Special Libraries Assoc.; Resistance: LNM; Male Chauvenist; LNM - Lexington ACS, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 17-46)
  - Talks - Philosophy Club; LNM - VA Academy of Science; CS3 Lunch - Reductionism; CS3 Lunch - Studying Anomalies; Contraversies on the Fringes; LNM - Conversazione, 1979-1985 (Box-folder 17-45)
  - Talks - Beyond Velikowsky; ICUS; SCI LIT - Choices and Challenges; SSE; Cornell - Contraversies & Fringe Science, 1985 (Box-folder 17-44)
  - Theory-Laden Facts - LNM, 1986 (Box-folder 17-40)
  - Toronto - Session on Resistance to Discovery, (Part I), 1980 (Box-folder 17-57)
  - Toronto - Session on Resistance to Discovery, (Part II), 1979-1980 (Box-folder 17-58)
  - Treat, 1990 (Box-folder 17-26)
  - U.S. Panel, Beyond Superstition, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 16-55)
  - VA Institute for Public Policy, 1997 (Box-folder 16-61)
  - VA Science Museum, 1996 (Box-folder 16-53)
  - VAS, 2001 (Box-folder 16-43)
  - Wax, 1983-2000 (Box-folder 16-28)
  - Western Ontario - LNM, 1988 (Box-folder 17-31)
  - What Makes Science Scientific?, 1990 (Box-folder 17-28)
  - Woods Hole, 1996 (Box-folder 16-50)
  - World Watch, 1991 (Box-folder 17-19)
  - W'Shop Hilton Head, 1979 (Box-folder 16-11)
- Teaching and Students
  - Chemistry files. (Box 7)
  - Class roles, 1986-1994. (Box 11)
  - Class roles and lectures, 1993-1996. (Box 12)
  - Communications from students. (Box 10)
  - Ethics, 1998 (Box-folder 18-2)
  - Ethics Seminar, 1997 (Box-folder 18-3)
  - Ethics Seminar - Historical, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 18-1)
  - HST 2354 Notes, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 18-7)
  - HST 4304 Notes, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 18-6)
  - Med School Seminar, 2007 (Box-folder 16-33)
  - Medical Ethics, 2001 (Box-folder 18-4)
  - Non-Studying Students - VT, 1993 (Box-folder 18-20)
  - Research Ethics - Seminar in Several Departments and Grad School Sponsored Course, 1999-2008 (Box-folder 18-5)
  - Society for Return to Academic Standards, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 18-18)
  - Student Decline - Nogueira Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 18-23)
  - Student evaluations. (Box 10)
  - Student Memorabilia, 1969-1978 (Box-folder 15-10)
  - Students Who Don't Study, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 18-19)
  - Students Who Don't Study - Correspondence, (Part I), 1996-2001 (Box-folder 18-21)
  - Students Who Don't Study - Correspondence, (Part II), 1993-1997 (Box-folder 18-22)
  - Overhead Projector Sheets
    - Anomalies, n.d. (Box-folder 18-17)
    - Education, n.d. (Box-folder 18-16)
    - Ethics - CS 3 Seminar, 1990 (Box-folder 17-25)
    - Evolution, n.d. (Box-folder 18-15)
    - Filter, n.d. (Box-folder 18-14)
    - Maps, n.d. (Box-folder 18-13)
    - Myth of S.M., n.d. (Box-folder 18-12)
    - Probabilities, n.d. (Box-folder 18-11)
    - SM vs. FP, n.d. (Box-folder 18-10)
    - Theory-Laden Ink Blots, n.d. (Box-folder 18-8)
    - Thermodynamics, n.d. (Box-folder 18-9)
    - Treat II, n.d. (Box-folder 17-27)
- Academic/Administration
  - 1983-1994 appointment books. (Box 12)
  - Associate Dean Successor, 1990 (Box-folder 17-20)
  - Campus Signage, n.d. (Box-folder 16-15)
  - CCAS Deans' Careers, 1991 (Box-folder 17-16)
  - Deaning, Evaluations, etc., 1978-1985 (Box-folder 16-4)
  - Dean's memoirs. (Box 3)
  - Jobs, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 15-12)
  - Kudos, Correspondence, Misc. Professional Activities, 1978-1995 (Box-folder 16-12)
  - Mandelstamm, 1991-2000 (Box-folder 16-14)
  - Misc files; Deanship; Sci Lit, 1998-1999. (Box 14)
  - Position Management, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 16-7)
  - Teacher course evaluations. (Box 10)
  - Vita, 1985-2010 (Box-folder 16-13)
  - VT- Misc., 1992-2001 (Box-folder 16-16)
- Subject/Administrative Files
  - Miscellaneous Files. (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Files. (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Files. (Box 13)
- Research
  - Books by Velikovsky. (Box 6)
  - Books on Velikovsky. (Box 5)
  - Chemistry grant reports. (Box 1)
  - Cryptozoology, 2003 (Box-folder 15-7)
  - Dimitri Bayanov, 1999-2004 (Box-folder 16-20)
  - Enigma correspondences. (Box 6)
  - Fred Eirich, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 16-22)
  - James P. Hogan, 2005 (Box-folder 16-23)
  - Kelikovsly. (Box 13)
  - Kronos. (Box 4)
  - Lee Edson, 1993-2006 (Box-folder 16-21)
  - Literature search. (Box 1)
  - Loch Ness. (Box 13)
  - Loch Ness clippings. (Box 3)
  - Loch Ness clippings. (Box 2)
  - Loch Ness correspondence. (Box 1)
  - Loch Ness correspondences. (Box 9)
  - Loch Ness correspondences. (Box 8)
  - Mackal archives. (Box 8)
  - Mike Swords, 2005 (Box-folder 16-26)
  - Misc. on Unorthodoxies, 1981-2001 (Box-folder 16-19)
  - NSF: LNM, Velikowsky, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 16-1)
  - Patrick Huyghe, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 16-25)
  - Re: Velikovsky, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 16-27)
  - Sci Lit correspondences. (Box 6)
  - Velikovsky References. (Box 9)
  - Velikovsky's sources part 1-6. (Box 5)
  - What Josef Martin Didn't Say, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 16-5)